Guide to the Mansfield Center for Pacific Affairs Records 1980-1998
Maureen and Mike Mansfield Library, The University of Montana-Missoula
Mansfield Center for Pacific Affairs records
1980-1998
University of Montana, Mansfield Library, Archives and Special Collections The University of Montana—Missoula Missoula, MT 59812 406-243-2053 http://www.lib.umt.edu/asc library.archives@umontana.edu
RG 33
Mansfield Center for Pacific Affairs
8.25 linear feet
This collection includes administrative files, published materials, and audio-visual media produced by the Mansfield Center for Pacific Affairs. The Center was founded to encourage strong understanding and improved relations between the western United States and the nations of the Pacific Rim.
Historical Note
The Mansfield Center for Pacific Affairs was founded in 1980 to encourage strong understanding and improved relations between the western United States and the nations of the Pacific Rim, in recognition of the outstanding work of Mike Mansfield in international relations in the Pacific. The Center was funded by the Mansfield Foundation and maintained offices at University of Montana's Maureen and Mike Mansfield Library, in Washington, DC, and in Tokyo. It planned an administrative and conference facility on Flathead Lake in western Montana, but was unable to construct this facility. It sponsored the Mike Mansfield Fellowship program, publications, and symposia on contemporary issues, and focused programs on public affairs and commerce, the humanities, and the arts.
In 2003 the board of the Maureen and Mike Mansfield Foundation voted to change the name of the Mansfield Center for Public Affairs to the Maureen and Mike Mansfield Foundation, as the two operated as a single legal entity.
This collection contains correspondence, financial records, and subject files that document the operations of the Mansfield Center for Pacific Affairs from 1980-1996 as well as a few published materials detailing the history of the Center and its activities. In addition to the Center's administrative files, this collection also contains masters and copies of media produced by the Center. The audio-visual media contained in this collection include video and audio masters for a documentary about Asian immigrants in the western United States titled From the Far East to the Old West: Chinese and Japanese Settlers in Montana. The collection also includes audio recordings of oral histories and their corresponding transcripts, edit logs, photographs, and artwork. Copies of the oral history audio cassettes and the transcripts comprise Oral History collection 436.
This collection is divided into two subgroups: Administrative Records and From the Far East to the Old West: Chinese and Japanese Settlers in Montana, production components.
Subgroup I, Administrative Records, consists of four series:
Series I: Correspondence, 1980-1987, 0.9 linear feet
Series II: Financial Records, 1985-1989, four folders
Series III: Subject Files, 1980-1994, 2.1 linear feet
Series IV: Published Materials, 1993-1996, 1 folder
Subgroup II, From the Far East to the Old West: Chinese and Japanese Settlers in Montana, production components consists of four series:
Series I: Video and Audio Masters, undated, 3.5 linear feet
Series II: Oral History Interviews, audio cassettes, 1998 and undated, 0.2 linear feet
Series III: Edit logs and Oral History Transcripts, undated, 0.2 linear feet
Series IV: Production Artwork, Photographs, and Other Images, 1998 and undated, 1.2 linear feet
Researchers must use collection in accordance with the policies of Archives and Special Collections, the Maureen and Mike Mansfield Library, and The University of Montana-Missoula.
The collection was in the possession of the Mansfield Center for Pacific Affairs until donation to the Archives.
Most of the administrative records were donated in 1991. The bulk of the production components for From the Far East to the Old West: Chinese and Japanese Settlers in Montana were donated in 2002 but the photos, zip disks and photo logs were donated in 2005.
Archives and Special Collections also holds records for the Maureen and Mike Mansfield Foundation, RG 034.
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the online catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search the catalog using these headings.
Mansfield Center for Pacific Affairs--Archives; Maureen and Mike Mansfield Foundation; Mike Mansfield Fellowship Program
Montana--Emigration and immigration--History; Montana--History; Pacific Area--Relations--West (U.S.); West (U.S.)--Relations--Pacific Area
Chinese--Montana--History; Japanese Americans--Montana--History; Pacific Area cooperation
Audiovisual materials; Interviews; Oral histories; Photographs
Montana; Chinese Americans; Japanese Americans
- Administrative records, 1980-1996; Subgroup I; 3.25 linear feet
  - Correspondence, 1980-1987; Series I; 0.9 linear feet
    This series contains correspondence produced by the Center.
    The materials were arranged chronologically by subject.
    - 1980-1982 (Box-folder 1/1)
    - 1983-1985 (Box-folder 1/2)
    - July 1986 (Box-folder 1/3)
    - August 1986 (Box-folder 1/4)
    - September 1986 (Box-folder 1/5)
    - October 1986 (Box-folder 1/6)
    - November 1986 (Box-folder 1/7)
    - December 1986 (Box-folder 1/8)
    - January 1987 (Box-folder 2/1)
    - February 1987 (Box-folder 2/2)
    - Conference, August 1985 (Box-folder 2/3)
    - Mike Mansfield, 1980-1983 (Box-folder 2/4)
    - Presidential search, 1985 (Box-folder 2/5)
    - Site selection, 1984 (Box-folder 2/6)
    - Site selection, 1985 (Box-folder 2/7)
    - Site selection, January-February 1986 (Box-folder 2/8)
    - Site selection, March-December 1986 (Box-folder 2/9)
  - Financial records, 1985-1989; Series II; 4 folders
    - Audit, 1985 (Box-folder 2/10)
    - Financial Report, 1985 (Box-folder 7/1)
    - Balance sheet, March 1988 (Box-folder 2/11)
    - Budget, 1988-1989 (Box-folder 2/12)
  - Subject files, 1980-1994; Series III; 2.1 linear feet
    - Committee, foreign advisory, 1980-1985 (Box-folder 3/1)
    - Committee, founding, 1982 (Box-folder 3/2)
    - Committee, nominating, 1985-1986 (Box-folder 3/3)
    - Feasibility study, Marts & Lundy, 1985-1986 (Box-folder 3/4)
    - Feasibility study, Marts & Lundy, 1986 (Box-folder 3/5)
    - Final report, Old West Regional Commission, September 1981 (Box-folder 3/6)
    - History, undated (Box-folder 3/7)
    - Meeting, June 1982 (Box-folder 3/8)
    - Reorganization, 1986 (Box-folder 3/9)
    - Reorganization, 1986 (Box-folder 3/10)
    - Flathead Lake Conference Center, architect, 1986 (Box-folder 3/11)
    - Flathead Lake Conference Center, architect, 1986 (Box-folder 4/1)
    - Flathead Lake Conference Center, architect, 1986 (Box-folder 7/2)
    - Flathead Lake Conference Center, engineering services, 1986 (Box-folder 4/2)
    - Flathead Lake Conference Center, preservation of Native American sites, 1986 (Box-folder 4/3)
    - Flathead Lake Conference Center, site programming, 1986 (Box-folder 4/4)
    - Flathead Lake Conference Center, site selection, 1985-1988 (Box-folder 4/5)
    - Flathead Lake Conference Center, site selection, 1985-1986 (Box-folder 4/6)
    - Flathead Lake Conference Center, clippings, 1984-1986 (Box-folder 4/7)
    - Flathead Lake Conference Center, feasibility study, 1982 (Box-folder 4/8)
    - Flathead Lake Conference Center, feasibility study, 1985-1986 (Box-folder 5/1)
    - Flathead Lake Conference Center, minutes, December 1985 (Box-folder 5/2)
    - Flathead Lake Conference Center, Piercy land gift, 1985-1989 (Box-folder 5/3)
    - Flathead Lake Conference Center, Zelezny/Murphy property, 1984-1991 (Box-folder 5/4)
    - Flathead Lake Conference Center, Zelezny/Murphy property, 1984-1991 (Box-folder 5/5)
    - Flathead Lake Conference Center, Painted Rocks, May-June 1985 (Box-folder 5/6)
    - Flathead Lake Conference Center, Painted Rocks, legal opinion, 1989 (Box-folder 5/7)
    - Flathead Lake Conference Center, reports, 1984-1986 (Box-folder 5/8)
    - Flathead Lake Conference Center, reports, 1982-1984 (Box-folder 5/9)
    - Flathead Lake Conference Center, reports, 1984 (Box-folder 6/1)
    - Flathead Lake Conference Center, reports, 1985 (Box-folder 6/2)
    - Flathead Lake Conference Center, reports, 1986 (Box-folder 6/3)
    - Flathead Lake Conference Center, negotiations, 1986 (Box-folder 6/4)
    - Flathead Lake Conference Center, site marketing survey, 1986-1987 (Box-folder 6/5)
    - Flathead Lake Conference Center, Sale of Zelezny/Murphy property, 1993-1994 (Box-folder 6/6)
    - Flathead Lake Conference Center, Sale of Zelezny/Murphy property, 1993-1994 (Box-folder 6/7)
  - Published Materials, 1993-1996 and undated; Series IV; 1 folder
    This series contains materials published by the Center about its history and activities. Most relate to events hosted by the Center.
    The materials were arranged chronologically.
    - Miscellaneous publications, 1993-1996 and undated (Box-folder 7/3)
- From the Far East to the Old West: Chinese and Japanese Settlers in Montana, production components, 1998 and undated; Subgroup II; 5.0 linear feet
  - Video and audio masters, undated; Series I; 3.5 linear feet
    Materials in this series include several audio-visual formats, including Beta and VHS videotapes, CDs, and DV video.
    - Beta original #1 (Box 1)
    - Beta original #2 (Box 1)
    - Beta original #3 (Box 1)
    - Beta original #4 (Box 1)
    - Beta original #5 (Box 1)
    - Beta original #5 (Box 1)
    - Beta original #6 (Box 1)
    - Beta original #7 (Box 1)
    - Beta original #8 (Box 1)
    - Beta original #9 (Box 1)
    - Beta original #10 (Box 1)
    - Beta original #11 (Box 1)
    - Beta original #12 (Box 1)
    - Beta original #13 (Box 1)
    - Beta original #14 (Box 1)
    - Beta original #15 (Box 1)
    - Beta original #16 (Box 1)
    - Beta original #17 (Box 1)
    - Beta original #18 (Box 1)
    - Beta original #19 (Box 1)
    - Beta original #20 (Box 1)
    - Beta original #21 (Box 1)
    - Beta original #22 (Box 1)
    - Beta original #23 (Box 1)
    - Beta original #24 (Box 1)
    - Beta original #25 (Box 1)
    - Beta original #26 (Box 1)
    - Beta original #27 (Box 1)
    - Beta original #28 (Box 1)
    - Beta original #29 (Box 1)
    - Beta original #30 (Box 1)
    - Beta original #31 (Box 1)
    - Beta original #32 (Box 1)
    - Beta original #33 (Box 1)
    - Beta original #34 (Box 1)
    - Beta original #35 (Box 1)
    - Beta original #36 (Box 1)
    - Beta original #37 (Box 1)
    - Beta original #38 (Box 1)
    - Beta original #39 (Box 2)
    - Beta original #40 (Box 2)
    - Beta original #41 (Box 2)
    - Beta original #42 (Box 2)
    - DV Train and Bannock (Box 2)
    - NCMG – Matt Hocevar, Japan Globe (Box 2)
    - NCMG – Matt Hocevar, China Globe (Box 2)
    - NCMG – Matt Hocevar (Box 2)
    - NCMG – Matt Hocevar (Box 2)
    - Asian beta offline edit (From Far East to Old West offline edit) (Box 2)
    - Asian VHS offline edit (From Far East to Old West offline edit) (Box 2)
    - Graphic sample (Box 2)
    - VHS copy of film purchased from Archives Films (Box 2)
    - Voiceover CD (Box 2)
    - Voiceover CD (Box 2)
    - Voiceover audiocassette (Box 2)
    - Narration - All takes CD (Box 2)
    - Narration - All takes DAT tape (Box 2)
    - Joyce Chinn, Railroad tracks CD (Box 2)
    - CD ROM of after-effects movies, Photoshop pics, Targa files, etc. (Box 2)
    - CD soundtrack, From Far East to Old West (Box 2)
    - Betacam SP master, From Far East to Old West (Box 2)
    - Archives films beta cassette of stock footage of "Asian settlers," viewing only (Box 2)
    - Footage filmed by Polar Bear Co., VHS #1, viewing only (Box 2)
    - Footage filmed by Polar Bear Co., VHS #2, viewing only (Box 2)
    - Footage filmed by Polar Bear Co., VHS #3, viewing only (Box 2)
    - Footage filmed by Polar Bear Co., VHS #4, viewing only (Box 2)
    - Footage filmed by Polar Bear Co., VHS #5, viewing only (Box 2)
  - Oral history interviews, audio cassettes, 1998, undated; Series II; 0.2 linear feet
    This series consists of audio recordings of interviews with individuals named below. Copies of these tapes are available as Oral History collection 436.
    - Linda Tamura interview, September 26, 1998 (Box 2)
    - Ding Tam interview and Losh Kusumoto interview, 1998 (Box 2)
    - Losh Kusumoto interview, August 13, 1998 (Box 2)
    - Bob Swartout interview, July 21, 1998 (Box 2)
    - Bob Swartout interview, July 21, 1998 (Box 2)
    - Liping Zhu interview and Henry Muneta interview, July 22, 1998 (Box 2)
    - Liping Zhu interview and Henry Muneta interview, July 22, 1998 (Box 2)
    - Henry Muneta interview and Robert Koyama interview, July, 1998 (Box 2)
    - Robert Koyama interview and Chrystal Shors interview, July, 1998 (Box 2)
    - Jim Kurokawa interview and Ben Harada interview, July, 1998 (Box 2)
    - Joyce Chinn interview, tape #1, January 22, 1998 (Box 2)
    - Joyce Chinn interview, tape #2, January 22, 1998 (Box 2)
    - Mr. Watanabe interview, undated (Box 2)
  - Edit logs and oral history transcripts, undated; Series III; 0.2 linear feet
    This series contains transcripts of the oral history interviews with the individuals named below. Copies of these transcripts are available as Oral History collection 436.
    - Edit logs (Box-folder 3/1)
    - Transcript list (Box-folder 3/2)
    - Transcript of Joyce Chinn interview, January 22, 1998 (Box-folder 3/3)
    - Transcript of Ben Harada interview, July 9, 1998 (Box-folder 3/4)
    - Transcript of Rick Harda interview, July 8, 1998 (Box-folder 3/5)
    - Transcript of Robert Koyama interview, July 23, 1998 (Box-folder 3/6)
    - Transcript of Jim Kurokawa interview, July 10, 1998 (Box-folder 3/7)
    - Transcript of Heloshi Kusumoto interview, August 13, 1998 (Box-folder 3/8)
    - Transcript of Henry Muneta interview, July 22, 1998 (Box-folder 3/9)
    - Transcript of Chrystal Shors interview, July 21, 1998 (Box-folder 3/10)
    - Transcript of Bob Swartout interview, July 21, 1998 (Box-folder 3/11)
    - Transcript of Ding Tam interview, July 27, 1998 (Box-folder 3/12)
    - Transcript of Linda Tamura interview, September 26, 1998 (Box-folder 3/13)
    - Transcript of Liping Zhu interview, July 22, 1998 (Box-folder 3/14)
  - Production artwork, photographs and other images, 1898, undated; Series IV; 1.2 linear feet
    In addition to photos and images, this series also includes photo logs and computer disks.
    - Montana map title page artwork (Box-folder 3/15)
    - Color copy of charcoal of Asian miners, artwork (Box-folder 3/16)
    - Copies from Butte Archives (Box-folder 3/17)
    - Photos and copies from National Archives (Box-folder 3/18)
    - Photo and letter from Stumptown Historical Society (Box-folder 3/19)
    - Photo and copies from Library of Congress (Box-folder 3/20)
    - Photo from World Museum of Mining (Box-folder 3/21)
    - Photos from Beaverhead County Museum Archives (Box-folder 3/22)
    - Photos and copies from Montana Historical Society (Box-folder 3/23)
    - Photo from Roger-Viollet, 1898 (Box-folder 3/24)
    - Photos and copies from unidentified source (Box-folder 3/25)
    - Picture log (Box-folder 3/26)
    - Charcoal of Asian miners, original artwork (OS 5)
    - Montana Historical Society photo of card game in King’s Saloon (OS 5)
    - Three boxes of zip disks (Box 4)
    - Log book for photos and other images with zip disk reference numbers (Box 4)